A Guide to the James Branch Cabell Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #5298-v
James Branch Cabell Collection 1932-1956
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
5298-v
24 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer, 1992 June 24
Item Listing
- Letters
  - James Branch Cabell, Richmond, to John Cook Wyllie, 1932 Mar 25; TLS, 1 p.
    [Thanks Wyllie for sending a magazine which proved to be of strong interest to Cabell.]
  - John Cook Wyllie, University of Virginia, to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1937 May 29; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Asks Cabell for one of the ninety-seven copies of his book discussing Ellen Glasgow for the Virginia collection of rare books and manuscripts at the University of Virginia. ]
  - James Branch Cabell, Richmond, to John Cook Wyllie, 1938 Apr 7; TLS, 1 p.
    [Expresses pleasure after reading his article on contemporary Virginia literature and confesses that he too has puzzled over "what a Virginian is?"]
  - Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., University of Virgina, to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1947 Mar 18; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Makes a case for Cabell leaving his papers and manuscripts in the care and safekeeping of the Manuscripts Department of the University of Virginia because 1) a great writer's papers should be at a University and neither of the two Richmond institutions is interested in collecting contemporary material and 2) the University of Virginia Library already has related papers, such as the Joseph C. Cabell Papers and the Cabell-Carrington Papers.]
  - James Branch Cabell, St. Augustine, Florida, to Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., University of Virginia, 1947 Mar 26; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Agrees to weigh carefully Berkeley's request to make the University of Virginia the repository for his papers and gives his best wishes ("unflavored with any special optimism") to the University in its pursuit of the Ellen Glasgow papers with Mrs. Van Doren.]
  - Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., University of Virginia, to James Branch Cabell, St. Augustine, Florida, 1947 Mar 31; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Thanks Cabell for giving serious consideration to his request for the University to be the depository of his papers and informs him of Mrs. Van Doren's response to his letter seeking the Ellen Glasgow papers, "So far there has been no decision made about the permanent disposal of Miss Glasgow's papers and manuscripts. I may say, however, that Mr. Morley and I have discussed --and with considerable favor --the University of Virginia as a repository."]
  - Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., University of Virgina, to James Branch Cabell, St. Augustine, Florida, 1948 Mar 2; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Notifies Cabell of "a beautiful group of Cabell first editions" given to the Library by Mrs. T. Catesby Jones which includes the New York, 1919,
    Jurgen
    , and the London
    of 1921, and makes another plea for Cabell's papers.]
  - James Branch Cabell, St. Augustine, Florida, to Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., 1948 Mar 6; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Acknowledges news of the gift of Mrs. T. Catesby Jones to the Library of Cabell first editions with the comment, "I admit that I very much dislike the first edition of any book by me, upon the rational ground that it invariably contains errors which the printer and I have united to contribute."]
  - James Branch Cabell, Poynton Lodge, Ophelia, Virginia, to Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., 1953 Jul 27; TLS, 1 p.
    [Informs Berkeley that although he has spent all spring weeding out his files and papers keeping only those items he was willing to preserve he has not yet decided upon their ultimate deposition.]
  - Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. to James Branch Cabell, Poynton Lodge, Ophelia, 1953 Jul 30; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Discusses some advantages to an author who has a depository institution willing to cooperate with him to preserve his work and offers again to preserve them at the University of Virginia. ]
  - James Branch Cabell, Richmond, to John Cook Wyllie, 1955 Nov 13; TLS, 1 p.
    [Shares his delight with Wyllie's review of his book
    As I Remember It
    but takes him to task for accusing him of "getting even" with Ellen Glasgow"whom I both loved and admired. She was, in addition to her other talents, a shrewd business woman who made the very utmost of her resources. That is all I had meant to convey"; he also expresses his joy that the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia is going to publish Mrs. Frances J. Brewer's Cabell bibliography.]
  - John Cook Wyllie to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1955 Nov 16; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Describes the progress with Mrs. Frances Brewer's Cabell bibliography which is to be published by the University of Virginia Press, offers to send a set of the galley proofs of the bibliography to Cabell and defends his discussion of Cabell and Ellen Glasgow in his review of Cabell's book.]
  - James Branch Cabell, Richmond, to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 Jan 7; TLS, 1 p.
    [Asks for Wyllie to please send a set of the galley proofs of Mrs. Brewer's bibliography of his work and offers to suggest any recent additions that she may have missed; he also hesitates to write a preface to the fourth bibliography of his work because he feels that the theme may be exhausted but promises to see what he can do.]
  - James Branch Cabell, Richmond, to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 Apr 23; TLS, 1 p.
    [Asks when Mrs. Brewer's bibliography will be published as he is leaving for the summer cottage where he will have little data with which to check any galley proofs.]
  - John Cook Wyllie to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1956 Apr 25; TLS (C), 2 p.
    [Discusses in great detail improvements that he believes should be made in Mrs. Brewer's Cabell bibliography by employing the Hinman collator.]
  - James Branch Cabell to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 May 1; TLS, 1 p.
    [Confesses that he believes it will be impossible and unnecessary to compare all of his various editions on the Hinman machine as most of the changes were to correct errors by the printers and were not really revisions.]
  - John Cook Wyllie to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1956 May 15; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Concedes that regarding his suggestions about the Cabell bibliography "that of the things that are necessary, only some of them are possible" and asks Cabell to let him know when he will return to Richmond in the fall "so that I can start annoying you anew."]
  - James Branch Cabell, Poynton Lodge, Ophelia, to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 Aug 29; TLS, 1 p.
    [Believes Desmond Tarrant's
    Towards Jerusalem
    , for which he answered questions and supplied some general commentaries, was excellent, suggests he submit his treatise to the Bibliographical Society, and asks Wyllie to answer as many of Mrs. Brewer's questions as he can.]
  - John Cook Wyllie to James Branch Cabell, Poynton Lodge, Ophelia, 1956 Sep 10; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Informs Cabell that he has answered Mrs. Brewer's inquiries and that he is immersed in Desmond Tarrant's critical study of
    . ]
  - James Branch Cabell, Poynton Lodge, Ophelia, to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 Sep 17; TLS, 1 p.
    [Describes the visit of Mrs. Brewer to Poynton Lodge and asks his opinion of Tarrant's treatise.]
  - James Branch Cabell, Richmond, to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 Oct 24; TLS, 1 p.
    [Informs him of his decision to sell some of his manuscripts and to present others to various libraries, including the University of Virginia and asks for a list of competent appraisers.]
  - John Cook Wyllie to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1956 Nov 1; TLS (C), 1 p.
    [Sends the first galleys of both Mrs. Brewer's bibliography and Matthew Bruccoli's supplementary notes on the collections at the University of Virginia. ]
  - John Cook Wyllie to James Branch Cabell, Richmond, 1956 Nov 8; TLS (C), 2 p.
    [Encloses a copy of Matthew Bruccoli's unfavorable assessment of
    which parallels his own view that the book would need considerable reworking.]
  - James Branch Cabell to John Cook Wyllie, 1956 Nov 11; TLS, 1 p.
    [Recommends that he write Tarrant "that the book, while containing much that is fine, needs overhauling. In the version that I have, the entire first fourth of the typescript is devoted to recent American authors in general, with just an occasional mention of Cabell --which is disproportionate, and would bewilder at outset almost any reader as to what exactly the book is to be about. These three chapters should be made into one chapter." He also believes that Tarrant should discuss more of his works than just the eighteen that are mentioned.]